Leo Goldschmidt Photograph Collection, 1878-1899 MS 437
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Leo Goldschmidt Photograph Collection 1878-1899, (bulk 1880-1889)
Collection Number: MS 437
Goldschmidt, Leo
Glass plate negatives and some printed material, 1878-1899 (bulk 1880-1889). The bulk of the material is comprised of the photographic plates taken by Leo Goldschmidt, a pioneer of the Tucson area. The plates cover a range of persons, subjects and locations, including; family, businesses, personal residences in Arizona and Sonora, Mexico.
2 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
None
Biographical Note
Leo Goldschmidt was born September 15, 1852 in Hamburg, Germany, died January 25, 1944 in Tucson, Arizona. Goldschmidt came to the United States at the age of eighteen where he later became a successful businessman and amateur photographer.
He began his business career in New Mexico with his brother, Adolf and moved to Tucson Arizona in 1878 where he opened a furniture store that later became the furniture department of the Zeckendorf and Steinfeld department stores. In 1888, he bought the Eagle Flour Milling Company and built it into the most modern mills of its time. He was also a director of the Consolidated National Bank which later became the Valley National Bank and is now Chase Bank.
The glass plates cover a range of persons, subjects and locations including family, businesses, personal residences in the Arizona and Sonora, Mexico area. One of his four sisters, Eva, was married to Jacob Mansfeld, another pioneer in the Tucson area.
This Collections is arranged into 3 series
Series 1: People 1880-1899
Series 2: Subjects 1880-1899
Series 3: Places 1880-1899
Glass plate negatives (bulk 1880-1899). The bulk of the collection is comprised of glass plates of Leo Goldschmidt and family members at their Tucson residences. Goldschmidt was never married and many of his photographs are of his nieces and nephews. The collection also consists of plates of Goldschmidt businesses and places of interest in Arizona, such as the Eagle Milling Company, San Xavier Del Bac Mission and the University of Arizona.
University of Arizona Special Collections, Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives, SJA 002 Arizona Historical Society/Tucson, Goldschmidt photograph collection, ca. 1885-1920.
Goldschmidt, Leo, 1852-1944 -- Photographs.; Goldschmidt family -- Photographs.; Mansfeld family -– Photographs; Campana Mill (Sonora, Mexico) -– Photographs; Eagle Flour Mill (Tucson, Ariz.)-- Photographs; Mission San Xavier del Bac (Tucson, Ariz.) -– Photographs; Old Main (Tucson, Ariz.) -– Photographs; Owl’s Club (Tucson, Ariz.) -- Photographs; University of Arizona -– Photographs; Bankers -– Arizona -– Tucson -– History; Businessmen -– Arizona -– Tucson -- History.; Flour mills -– Arizona -– Tucson -- History; Furniture industry and trade -– Arizona -– Tucson -- History; Merchants – Arizona – Tucson – History; Pioneers -– Arizona – Tucson -- History; Baboquivari Peak (Ariz.) -– Photographs; Sentinel Peak (Tucson, Ariz.) -– Photographs; Santa Cruz River (Ariz. and Mexico) -– Photographs; Sonora (Mexico: State) -– History -– Photographs; Tucson (Ariz.) -– History -– Photographs; glass negatives
- Series I: People, 1880-1899
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains glass plates of Leo Goldschmidt’s sisters, nieces, nephews and other family members in Tucson, Arizona. It also contains plates of Leo Goldschmidt and others at one of his places of business, La Campana Mill in Sonora, Mexico.
  - Bertho and nurse, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Eza, Beckie and friend under an umbrella, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fenner, Gibbon & Rocha in Gibbons yard1890 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fenner, Mrs., Miss Henmore and Mr. Blake (by Herbert Tenney)1800s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gertrude1887 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gilchrist and myself at El Grupo Sonora1895 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Goldschmidt sisters: Mrs. Adolf Goldschmidt, Mrs. Erce Mansfeld, Mrs. Gertrude Florsheim, Mrs. Aaron Zeckendorf, Mrs. Helen Leventhal1880s, 2 plates (Box 1, Folder 7,8)
  - Goldschmidt, Doris1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Goldschmidt, Leo1800s, 2 plates (Box 1, Folder 10, 11, 12)
  - Goldschmidt, Leo (bedroom)1800s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Goldschmidt, Leo (yard)1800s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Goldschmidt, Leo (?) Portrait of man1800s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Goldschmidt, Samuel – First baby picture1895 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Helen, Marianne and Hannah at Gibbon garden Tucson, Arizona1887 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Howe, Charlie on horseback1889 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Indian Duzlinga at El Toen Sonora, MéxicoFebruary 1897 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Luke and his barnyard at El Grupo (Sonora, Mexico)July 1896 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mansfeld, Eva1888 or 1889 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mansfeld, Sammie on bike1894, 3 plates (Box 2, Folder 2, 3, 4)
  - Phyllis, Jeanne Z (Zeckendorf?) and two friends in Mansfeld Yard Tucson, Arizona 1894 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified Kids dancing (family)1800s) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified kids on a step ladder 18951895, 2 plates (Box 2, Folder 7, 8)
  - Unidentified man 1800s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified man at writing table in a bedroom1800s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified man in glasses1800s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified men sitting at table reading1800s, Broken plate (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified Mexicans boys playing marbles1894 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified people with W.J. Gibbon 1890, Broken plate (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified woman1800s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified woman in chair1800s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Unidentified woman with young boy and rocking horse1800s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified women at table/fireplace1800s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified young boy1800s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified young boy on rocking horse1800s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Unidentified young man 1800s (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Unidentified young mancirca 1899 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Unidentified young men1800s (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Tenney, Herbert & Herford, Frank under fig tree in Gibbon yard1800s, Broken plate (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Series II: Subjects, 1880-1899
  Arrangement: Geographical by Arizona and Sonora, Mexico, Alphabetical.
  This series contains glass plates of the exterior and interior of Leo Goldschmidt’s place of residence, The Owl’s Club. Also included are general subjects of interest to Mr. Goldschmidt as a photographer such as the Mission San Xavier del Bac, the University of Arizona and various street scenes of Tucson, Arizona in the late 1800s. The series also contains plates of the Eagle Flour Mill in Tucson, Arizona and the Campana Mill and various, associated buildings of the business in Sonora, Mexico.
  - Canvas tent in landscape Tohons? Stockade?1800s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Church building Exterior view1800s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Church Plaza “Old Catholic Church” St. Augustine Cathedral1896 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Cows in field1890s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cows under trees1890s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dog sitting on rug1890s, 2 plates (Box 3, Folder 6, 7)
  - Eagle Mill and tanksJuly 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Eagle Mill Belts and Machines1880s, 2 plates (Box 3, Folder 9, 10)
  - Eagle Mill from South Main Street1895 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Eagle Mill Interior 4th Floor Daylight1890s, 4 plates (Box 3, Folder 12, 13, 14, 15)
  - Eagle Mill Interior 4th Floor Flashlight – Leo Goldschmidt1890s (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Eagle Mill Roller Floor1890s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Eagle Mill Third Floor1800s (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Eagle Milling Company Roller Process Floor mills1890s, Broken plate (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Episcopal Church (Tucson, Arizona) 1895 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Episcopal Church (Tucson, Arizona) left side, blurred 1895 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Landscape – Unidentified Building1890s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Landscape - Unidentified Building and water tanks1890s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - New Eagle Flour Mills (Tucson, Arizona) 1899 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Old Eagle Mill on South Main Street shortly after purchase from E.N. Fish1890, Broken plate (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Owl’s Club - Bedroom1895, 3 plates (Box 4, Folder 7, 8, 9)
  - Owl’s Club Christmas decorations1895 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Owl’s Club - Dining room1890s (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Owl’s Club - Dining room with fireplace1890s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Owl’s Club - Dr. Fenner’s House-The Owls original annex1892 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Owl’s Club - Interior of residence sitting/living room1890s (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Owl’s Club - Interior residence table1890s (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Owl’s Club - My room (no info.)1890s (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Owl’s Club on Main Street - facade of building 1890s (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Owl’s Club - Sitting/living room 1890s (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Owl’s Club - Unidentified room 1890s (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Owl’s Club – Unidentified room with stairway 1890s (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Royal A. Johnson’s Iceworks 1889 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Saginaw Mill Exterior 1800s (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - San Xavier del Bac (Tucson, Arizona) Exterior 1887 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - San Xavier del Bac (Tucson, Arizona) Interior 1887 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - San Xavier Hotel Tucson, Arizona1890 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - San Xavier Mission – Mortuary chapel Tucson, Arizona1888, Broken plate) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Southern Pacific Depots (Slide said: California East Freight line)1890 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified building1890s, Broken plate (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - University of Arizona Panorama 1800s (Box 5, Folder 9, 10, 11, 12)
  - Panorama View of Tucson 1800s (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Panorama View of Tucson Mountains 1800s (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - University of Arizona, Old Main (Tucson, Ariz.) 1895 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Campana Mill1897 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Campana Mill February1897 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Campana Mill Blacksmith Shopcirca 1896-1897 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Campana Mill – Brush houseFebruary 1897 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Campana Mill-Front view1897 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Campana Mill-Side view1897 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - El Grupo Sonora (Mexico) - Assay Office & tankscirca 1896-1897 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - El Grupo Store & San Joaquin Ranch House1896 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Panorama of El Grupo Mill??? House from Reservoir DamJuly 1896 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - El Grupo Sonora (Mexico) - Superintendent’s House and 2 unidentified people1896 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - “Place de la Bastille” copy (Paris, France)1890s
- Series III: Places, 1880-1899
  Arrangement: Alphabetical.
  - Baboquivari Park from Buenos Ayres1897 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Bear Canyon, Catalina Mountains taken by Prof. Tommey1896 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Main Street looking North 1895 (Tucson, Arizona)1895 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Santa Cruz River Scene (Tucson, Arizona)1892 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Sentinel Park (Tucson Mountains, Arizona)1895 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Silver Lake (Tucson, Arizona)1888 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Silver Lake (Tucson, Arizona) (Broken plate)1888 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Some old willow trees (Tucson, Arizona) River below Main Street1892 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - South Main Ave. (Tucson, Arizona)1890 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - South Main Street Eagle Mills1895 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Tucson, Arizona from Ice Works1887 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified Panorama (Old sleeve says “Iron Horse”)circa 1800 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Prints, 1880-1899
  Arrangement: Box level.
  - Box 1 prints, Series I: People1880-1889 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Box 2 prints, Series I: People1880-1889 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Box 3 prints, Series II: Subjects1880-1889 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Box 4 prints, Series II: Subjects1880-1889 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Box 5 prints, Series II: Subjects1880-1889 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Box 6 prints, Series II: Subjects1880-1889 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Box 7 prints, Series III: Places1880-1889 (Box 8, Folder 7)